A Guide to the Papers of Winston Churchill 1897-1933
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Winston Churchill 1897-1933
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7501
38 items.
Forms part of the Clifton Waller Barrett Library of American Literature
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Clifton Waller Barrett
Biographical/Historical Information
American novelist and political reformer.
Scope and Content Information
The collection consists of letters from Churchill to various editors and publishers.
Arrangement
The letters are in chronological order
Contents List
- Letter to Alexander Wilson Drake 1897 April 25, ALS, 2 p.
  Reports that current proofs are lacking corrections Churchill made to correspond to Mr. Clinemot's pictures; gives him authority to make changes to suit the illustrations as he will be working for the Navy Dept. for the duration of the war.
- Letter to Clarence Clough Buel 1897 October 18, ALS, 2 p.
  Wants to know when Century Magazine will publish his story; McMillan Company is publishing The Celebrity in early spring. A note on top initialed by Buel states that Churchill might write another story as good as Elopement.
- Letter to Richard Watson Gilder 1899 March 28, TLS, 1 p.
  His book [ Richard Carvel] will be published by MacMillan in May. Intends to write a series of Naval Academy stories; hopes they will be published in the spring of the next year; asks if the Century is interested in publishing several. Note at the bottom by [Gilder?] expresses interest; hopes to publish some.
- Letter to Richard Watson Gilder 1899 July 29, TLS, 2 p.
  Recounts the negotiations concerning the publication of a new novel [ The Crisis]; describes its setting; hopes to finish by June and is anxious to have it published serially in Century
- Letter from Richard Watson Gilder to My Dear Scott 1899 Jul 29, ALS, 2 p.
  Hopes to encourage Churchill to finish [ The Crisis] one month early so serial publication can begin in December.
- Letter to Richard Watson Gilder 1899 August 5, ALS, 2 p.
  Working overtime to finish [ The Crisis]; Maxfield Parrish, who is waiting to hear from Alexander Wilson Drake, will do the drawings. Discusses creative methods; asks Gilder what he should read about George Dennison Prentice and what is the price of Battles and Leaders of the Civil War
- Letter to William Webster Ellsworth 1899 Aug 9, ALS, 6 p.
  Is unable to complete [ The Crisis] on time; wants time to research it thoroughly, rather than rush to finish; hopes Century and George Platt Brett will be willing to delay publication
- Letter to Richard Watson Gilder 1899 Aug 9, ALS, 6 p.
  It was against his better judgment to agree to a new time frame for [ The Crisis]; describes his friend Henry Hitchcock, a prominent citizen in St. Louis during the book's time period; believes that a trip to St. Louis is necessary for additional research; wants to take advantage of the popularity of Richard Carvel; hopes Brett will agree to delay publication.
- Letter to William Webster Ellsworth 1899 Aug 14, ALS, 2 p.
  Feels he was wrong to write [ The Crisis] in a serial format; will talk to Brett about beginning serial publication in May. Very pleased with Battles and Leaders of the Civil War which will prove invaluable in his new work.
- Letter to Silas Weir Mitchell 1899 Dec 23, ALS, 4 p.
  Refers to criticism that Richard Carvel aped Hugh Wynne; avoided reading it while working on his book so he would not imitate; enjoyed reading it and awaits the next installment of Autobiography of a Quack; grateful for Mitchell's advice about taking time.
- Letter to Richard Watson Gilder 1900 Jan 24, TLS, 1 p.
  Spending winter gathering material in St. Louis; glad he did not proceed last fall because of the amount of material he has found; thinks [ The Crisis] will be very long; will remember his promise to Gilder if it is available for serial publication; thanks Gilder for George Dennison Prentice poems; will read the biographical note with great interest.
- Letter to Miss B. Bondy 1900 Feb 1, TLS, 1 p.
  Discussed her proposition to translate Richard Carvel into German with his publishers; they desire a reliable publisher; does she know any; hopes to make satisfactory arrangements.
- Letter to Richard Watson Gilder 1900 Feb 8, TLS, 1 p.
  Discusses the personality of George Dennison Prentice and is grateful that Gilder called his attention to him. Has drafted 13 chapters of [ The Crisis]; the magnitude of the project and the need for accuracy has slowed it down; assures Gilder that if it is published serially he will get it; has received a letter from Mitchell that he prizes highly.
- Letter to Robert Underwood Johnson 1900 Apr 17, ALS, 3 p.
  Assures him that the Century will have serial rights to [ The Crisis]; has received an offer from Harpers Weekly but rejected it; informs him that the book will not be finished before late autumn; does not believe that it would be profitable to delay publishing the book in order to have it first appear in serial form; thinks that Brett will agree to delay publication for another year; desires to keep good will of all concerned.
- Letter to Robert Underwood Johnson 1900 Jul 5, TLS, 2 p.
  Refuses Johnson's proposal; must finish [ The Crisis] in time for late fall publication. Note on top reads "Good now go for him. C.F.C."
- Letter to Richard Watson Gilder 1900 Jul 23, TLS, 1 p.
  Will do his best to give The Century the story Johnson wishes; will probably not finish [ The Crisis] until late in the fall; recommends Herbert David Croly for publication, especially his essay on Robert Louis Stevenson.
- Letter to Robert Underwood Johnson 1900 Oct 8, TLS, 1 p.
  Cannot write a story for him until [ The Crisis] is finished; mentions the dramatization of The World's Almanac.
- Letter to Thomas Wentworth Higginson 1900 Nov 10, ALS, 1 p.
  Appreciates what he has done for him; will not be in Boston for the first meeting of the Round Table.
- Letter to Robert Underwood Johnson 1901 Feb 4, TLS, 1 p.
  Working eight hours a day finishing [ The Crisis]; still intends to do a story when he has the time.
- Letter to Lorin Fuller Deland 1901 Feb 19, ALS, 2 p.
  Declines to assume the duties of chairman of a committee as he is very absorbed in present work; hopes to finish[ The Crisis] in April; decided upon a play and Clemson should be back with the manuscript any day; recommends Clemson as the new chairman.
- Letter to Richard Watson Gilder 1901 May 3, ALS, 3 p.
  Is thinking of the requested short story; wants to take care with it; has finished[ The Crisis] and is exhausted; did not know that [Owen McMahon Johnson] wrote Arrows of the Almighty; will read it with great interest.
- Letter to Cyrus Townsend Brady 1901 Jun 27, TLS, 1 p.
  Thanks Brady for favorable review [of The Crisis]which is to appear in the Book Buyer July 1901 issue; high opinion of Brady's own work; considers their love for the Navy to be a common bond.
- Letter to John Kendrick Bangs 1901 Jul 11, ALS, 2 p.
  Welcomes the tribute of a 13 year old boy; surprised that he was interested in political history; will send an autograph copy [of The Crisis] to the boy.
- Letter to Robert Underwood Johnson 1904 Mar 25, TLS, 1 p.
  Is finishing The Crossing which has taken him three years to write; has not written a short story since By Order of the Admiral, which was printed in the Century, whose readers' opinions he values.
- Letter to George Higgins Moses 1906 Jun 23, TLS, 1 p.
  Thanks Moses for kind criticism of Coniston; hopes the book will help clean up politics.
- Letter to Robert Underwood Johnson 1906 Sep 21, TLS, 1 p.
  Thanks Johnson for editorial in the Saturday Evening Post
- Letter to Robert Underwood Johnson 1911 Sep 25, ALS, 1 p.
  Will bear in mind his advice; discusses his new book which he hopes will be better than any other he has written. Note to William Webster Ellsworth from Johnson at top of page that he has written to Churchill about how pleased he was that Ellsworth offered to publish the book, and disappointed that Churchill decided not to publish.
- Letter to Robert Underwood Johnson 1912 Feb 3, TLS, 1 p.
  Refers to meeting with Johnson and Clarence Clough Buel and Mr. Scott; Thinks it is a good decision that the Century did not publish Churchill's present story; does not think it is suitable for serial publication. Believes Tante to be "a very remarkable piece of work."
- Letter to Mr. [Gund?] 1913 Jun 11, ALS, 2 p.
  Gives best wishes to him as editor of the Century; offers the enclosed article [ The modern quest for religion]for publication; he delivered it as an address to the University of California.
- Letter to Mr. Harvey 1913 Aug 18, TLS, 2 p.
  Answers question regarding The Inside of the Cup; agrees with him that compromises are allowed in theology that would never be allowed in practical ethics; feels that he was right to keep his protagonist in the church; feels that the church of the future must maintain some forms and rituals.
- Letter to Mr. Harvey 1913 Sep 11, TLS, 1 p.
  Does not expect to be in New York until the spring; will address Harvey's club if time permits.
- Letter to Selig Polyscope Company 1916 May 4, TLS, 2 p.
  Explains why he wrote The Crisis and what he was portraying in it; admires Abraham Lincoln; believes the Civil War was the clash of the Puritan tradition in the North with the Royalist/Church of England tradition in the South; argues that these two traditions moved west and met in St. Louis where the novel was set; thinks that motion pictures have potential of educating people, but many of the ones he has seen are on a low plane of art.
- Letter to Dr. Douglas 1919 Jan 26, ALS, 2 p.
  Appreciates the invitation.
- Letter to Mrs. Wills 1926 Apr 5, ALS, 1 p.
  Does not want to sell film rights for any of his books.
- Letter to John 1928 Apr 20, ALS, 2 p.
  Discusses house and locale in Annapolis where character Richard Carvel lived.
- Letter to Mr. Langsdorf 1930 Feb 10, ALS, 3 p.
  Explains his religious philosophy; believes that the "Kingdom of God" is found within; offers advice on writing.
- Letter to N. J. Baratlett & Company 1928 Apr 20, TLS, 1 p.
  Asks for a copy of Themis by Jane Ellen Harrison.
- Letter to Hamilton Wright Mabie n.d., ALS, 2 p.
  Is sailing soon and will not be able to do the requested article.